Barbara McClintock Papers 1927-1991 Mss.Ms.Coll.79
American Philosophical Society
Barbara McClintock Papers
1927-1991
Mss.Ms.Coll.79
American Philosophical Society
70.5 Linear feet
The maize geneticist Barbara McClintock (1902-1992) is credited with the discovery of "jumping genes," that is chromosomal "crossing over" and translocation. She received the Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine in 1983. The collection is organized into six series: I. Correspondence, 1931-1991; II. Subject files, 1938-1989; III. Works by McClintock, 1944-1989; IV. Works by others, 1927-1991; V. Research notes, notebooks, and card files, 1930s-1990s; VI. Photographs, 1928-1991.
McClintock, Barbara, 1902-1992
Genetics Note
This collection contains materials which relate to the history of genetics.
Beadle, George Wells Correspondence (7 items) 1972-1981
Blumenschein, Almiro Correspondence (129 items) 1963-1973
Carnegie Institution of Washington Correspondence (75 items) 1967-1992
Emerson, Rollins Adams Correspondence (1 item) 1944
Green, Melvin Martin Correspondence (23 items) 1949-1984
Kato Yamakake, Takeo Angel Correspondence (2 folders) 1963-1984
Lederberg, Joshua Correspondence (5 items) 1948
McClintock, Barbara -- Bibliography Manuscripts (4 pages) Circa 1930s
McClintock, Barbara -- Curriculum Vitae Manuscripts (32 pages) 1965-1989
McClintock, Barbara -- Index to Plant Chromosome Numbers Manuscripts (9 folders) 1959-1965
McClintock, Barbara -- Nobel Prize Records (2 folders) 1983-1984, 1989
McClintock, Barbara -- Research notes and card files Notebooks (55 linear feet) 1930s-1990s
McClintock, Barbara -- Works Manuscripts (5 linear feet) 1944-1989
Wallace, Bruce Correspondence (23 items) Circa 1965 - 1982
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The McClintock Papers were donated to the APS Library by the estate of Barbara McClintock in 1992.
Scope and Contents note
The Barbara McClintock Papers (1927-1991) contain correspondence, subject files, manuscripts of published and unpublished works by McClintock, papers by colleagues and students, research notes by McClintock and by students, and photographs, which document McClintock's career as a maize geneticist. It was thought for some time, according to the data collected by the Genetics Society of America in the late 1970s (see Bentley Glass, A Guide to the Collections of the American Philosophical Society), that McClintock had destroyed all of her papers except the research notes. Fortunately, after McClintock's death it was discovered that not everything had been destroyed. The bulk of the collection dates from the 1960s to the 1990s; there are some earlier materials dating from 1927, which McClintock had probably meant to destroy, but which were mixed in with research notes. The collection is mainly in English, but there are a few items in other languages, such as French and Spanish. These latter folders are marked, for example, "Some in Spanish" or "In Spanish," as appropriate.
The papers (124 boxes; 70.5 linear feet) are divided into six series:
Series I. Correspondence, 1931-1991 (7 boxes; 3.25 linear feet)
Series II. Subject files, 1938-1989 (3 boxes; 1 linear foot)
Series III. Works by McClintcok, 1944-1989 (11 boxes; 5 linear feet)
Series IV. Works by others, 1927-1991 (10 boxes; 4.5 linear feet)
Series V. Research notes and card files, 1930s-1990s (88 boxes; 55 linear feet)
Series VI. Photographs, 1928-1991 (4 boxes; 1.5 linear feet)
Series I-VII. Oversize (1 box; .25 linear feet)
Materials of a personal nature appear in the following folders: Series I: Bhavnani, Mitz; Crowell, Mignon; Helfman, Arthur and Ruth; Willey, Genevra S.; Series II: McClintock, Sara and Thomas Henry -- 50th Wedding Anniversary; Series VI: Bhavnani, Mitz; Crowell, Frank and Mignon; McClintock, Sara; McClintock, Barbara, May 1985; McClintock, Barbara and David; McClintock, Barbara and Mitz Bhavnani; [McClintock, Malcolm Rider?]; McClintock, Sara and Mutty; McClintock Family; Unidentified, 1954, 1983, n.d.; Willey, Genevra S. and Tom.
Arrangement note
Oversized materials follow the same series arrangement as noted above. Cross-referencing to oversized material appears on the folders in the standard sized boxes. All photographs and negatives have been removed from Series I-V and placed in Series VI. Cross-references appear in the original series. Reprints have been moved to the printed materials collection of the APS library. If a reprint was found as an enclosure, a photocopy of the title page was filed in its place. To retrieve reprints, consult the card catalog for printed materials. One 45 rpm audio recording called "The DOUBLE Talking HELIX Blues", which was given to McClintock by Ira Herskowitz was also removed from the collection. To retrieve this item, consult the card catalog for manuscript materials.
Biographical/Historical note
Barbara McClintock, a maize geneticist, was born in Hartford, Connecticut on 16 June 1902. In 1908 her family moved to Brooklyn, New York, where her interest in science began at Erasmus Hall High School. When she finished high school in 1919, McClintock enrolled, despite her parents' opposition, at Cornell University's College of Agriculture. Since the College would not allow women to major in plant breeding, McClintock majored in botany. At the end of her junior year, after having taken a genetics course, she was invited to take the graduate course in genetics and was unofficially made a graduate student. She received her B.A. in 1923, at which time approximately 25% of the graduates from the College of Agriculture were women. She went on to receive her Ph.D. in botany in 1927; her thesis advisor was Lester Sharp, a cytology professor in the Botany Department.
McClintock remained at Cornell doing research for another four years. Then, receiving a fellowship from the National Research Council, she studied and taught at the University of Missouri, California Institute of Technology, and Cornell University between 1931 and 1933. Cornell remained her home base, even though the University did not offer her a job. (The first woman assistant professor at Cornell in a field other than home economics was not appointed until 1947.) In 1933, McClintock received a Guggenheim Fellowship to study in Germany but returned within the year due to the depressed, troubled conditions in Germany. (The geneticist Curt Stern, with whom she had been planning to study, had already left the country.)
McClintock again did research at Cornell until 1936, working in Rollins Emerson's laboratory supported by the Rockefeller Foundation. That year, she moved to the University of Missouri at Columbia, where she was Assistant Professor of Botany until 1940. At that time, not having been offered an incentive to stay, she went to Cold Spring Harbor with Marcus Rhoades where she studied maize until the following November. In December 1941, when Milislav Demerec became Director of the Department of Genetics of the Carnegie Institution of Washington at Cold Spring Harbor, he offered her a one-year position, which was later made permanent. She remained Staff Member at the Carnegie Institution until 1967, when she became Distinguished Service Member.
During her tenure at the Carnegie Institution McClintock was also Consultant (from 1962 to 1969) to the Agricultural Science Program of the Rockefeller Foundation, which funded research in maize in South America. Much of this work involved discussing research results with, among others, Takeo A. Kato Yamakake and Almiro Blumenschein, with whom she later wrote a book, Chromosome Constitution of Races of Maize.
McClintock traced genes through the changes in the colored kernels of maize. In the 1930s she discovered "crossing over," in which chromosomes break and recombine to create genetic changes. In the 1950s, she discovered the occurrence of transposable genetic elements and their effect on gene expression; that is, that genes are not fixed like pearls on a string but that they move or "jump" around. She found the first jumping gene on the short arm of chromosome 9. Because the gene broke the chromosome into two parts, she called the gene "DS" or dissociation element. She called the jumping genes "control elements" because they inactivated neighboring genes on the chromosome. The element, which causes the gene to jump, she called "AC" or activator element.
McClintock's findings were ignored, partly because the complex development patterns of maize were not as clear to everyone else (especially non-maize geneticists) as they were to her. In the 1970s, molecular biologists isolated transposable elements in bacteria and discovered that they were used by cells to control genes, revealing the same discovery that McClintock had made twenty years earlier in maize.
In time, McClintock's work was appreciated and lauded. She received many awards for her research in maize, including an Award of Merit from the Botanical Society of America (1957), the Kimber Genetics Award from the National Academy of Science (1967), the National Medal of Science (1970), the Louis and Bert Freedman Foundation Award for Research in Biochemistry (1978), the John D. and Catherine T. MacArthur Foundation Prize (1978), the Lewis S. Rosenstiel Award (1978), the Albert Lasker Basic Medical Research Award (1981), the Wolf Foundation Award (1981), the Louisa Gross Horwitz Prize (1982), the Charles Leopold Mayer Prize (1982), and the Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine (1983). McClintock was the first woman to win an unshared Nobel Prize in that category and the third woman to win an unshared Nobel Prize in science.
McClintock also received numerous honorary degrees, including those from Georgetown University, Harvard University, University of Cambridge, and Yale University. She was a member of various societies, including the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, the American Association for the Advancement of Science, the American Institute of Biological Sciences, the American Philosophical Society, the American Society of Naturalists, the Botanical Society of America, the Genetics Society of America (by which she was elected Vice President in 1939 and the first woman President in 1945), the National Academy of Sciences (she was the third woman ever elected), the National Women's Hall of Fame, the New York Academy of Sciences, and the Royal Society of London.
Barbara McClintock died on 2 September 1992 at age ninety.
Beadle, George Wells, 1903-1989; Blumenschein, Almiro; Brink, R. Alexander, (Royal Alexander), 1897-; Brown, W. L., (William L.), 1913-; Burnham, Charles R., (Charles Russel); Green, Melvin M.; Kato Yamakake, Takeo Angel, 1932-; Lederberg, Joshua; Nelson, Oliver Evans, Jr., 1920-; Peterson, Peter Andrew, 1925-; Rhoades, Marcus M., (Marcus Morton), 1903-1991; Shapiro, James Allen, 1943-; Sharp, Lester W., (Lester Whyland), b. 1887; Corn--Genetics.; Crossing over (Genetics); Laboratory notebooks; Laboratory notes; Lantern slides; Lectures; Maize--Genetics; National Medal of Science; Nobel Prizes; Photonegatives; Photoprints; Plant genetics; Translocation (Genetics).; Wolf Foundation Prize; Women botanists; Women geneticists; Women in science; Women scientists
- Series I. Correspondence, 1931-1992; 3.25 linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  Incoming and outgoing manuscript and typescript letters, carbons, telegrams, and postcards generated during McClintock's career. Series I is arranged alphabetically by correspondent's name and then chronologically within each folder. When a correspondence file includes letters to a third party (i.e., not McClintock), the name is indicated on the container list by using an indent under the folder title.
  Unidentified correspondence has been filed as "Unidentified" and is arranged chronologically.
  Enclosed manuscripts have been removed from this series and placed in Series III or IV as appropriate. As with the reprints, a photocopy of the title page was filed with the original letter. Cross-references are also given for enclosed photographs, which have been removed to Series VI. Letters of reference are filed under the name of the person who is the subject of the letter.
  Correspondents include geneticists, maize geneticists, biochemists, chemists, students, and some publishers. The bulk of this series covers the 1960s to the 1990s, and the major topic of this series is maize genetics. Much of the correspondence consists of detailed explanations of McClintock's and others' experimental findings. In some cases, McClintock sent seed packets to a correspondent and kept copies of the packets labeled with the seed type. These packets were photocopied, and the photocopies have been placed in the appropriate correspondent's folder. There is a large amount of correspondence with the Rockefeller Foundation regarding the consulting work she did with them for their Agricultural Science Program in South America. Much of this work involved Takeo A. Kato Yamakake and Almiro Blumenschein; there is also a large amount of correspondence with both of them.
  Correspondents in Series I include:
  Beadle, George W.
  Blumenschein, Almiro
  Brink, R. Alexander
  Brown, William L.
  Burnham, Charles R.
  Green, Melvin M.
  Kato Yamakake, Takeo Angel
  Lederberg, Joshua
  Nelson, Oliver E., Jr.
  Peterson, Peter A.
  Rhoades, Marcus M.
  Shapiro, James A.
  Sharp, Lester W.
  - Alberts, Bruce, 1970-1982 (Box 1)
  - Albrecht-Buehler, Guenter, 1983, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Anderson, Edgar, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Armstrong, F., [196-?] (Box 1)
  - Bard College, 1982-1983 (Box 1)
  - Barghoorn, Elso S. (Box 1)
    See Ser.I, Galinat, Walton C.
  - Barkan, Alice, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
    Martienssen, Robert
  - Barry, Edward G., 1961 (Box 1)
  - Beadle, George Wells, 1972-1981; 7.0 Item(s) (Box 1)
    Blumenschein, Almiro; Cytogenetics; History of biology, especially genetics; Kato Yamakake, Takeo Angel; Mangelsdorf, Paul C.; Publication; Zea (maize) genetics
  - Bhavnani, Mitz, 1977-1984 (Box 1)
  - Bird, Robert McK., 1978 (Box 1)
  - Blackburn, Elizabeth H., 1983 (Box 1)
  - Blanco, José L., [196-] (Box 1)
    In Spanish
  - Blumenschein, Almiro, 1963-1973; 129.0 Item(s) (Box 1)
    Some in Portguese
    Painter, Theophidus, 1969
    The Rockefeller Foundation
    Safont, Julio
    See also Ser.I, Brown, William L.
    See also Ser.I, The Rockefeller Foundation
    See also Ser.I, Safont, Julio
    See also Ser.I, Timothy, David H
    Conferences and symposia; Cytogenetics; Educational matters; Genetics of plants; Kato Yamakake, Takeo Angel; Publication; Research support; Research support -- Rockefeller Foundation; Statistics, biostatistics, biometrics; Travel -- Brazil; Travel -- Invitations, arrangements; Travel -- South America; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.; Zea (maize) genetics
  - Brandeis University. Rosenstiel Basic Medical Sciences Research Center, 1978 (Box 1)
    See also Ser.VI, Rosenstiel Award
  - Brieger, F.G., 1960-1966 (Box 1)
  - Brink, R. A[lexander], 1972 (Box 1)
  - Brookhaven National Laboratory, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Brown, William L., 1959-1967 (Box 1)
    Goodman, Major M.
    Hyland, Howard L.
    Monteiro, Warton
    Timothy, David H.
    See also Ser.I, Blumenschein, Almiro
    See also Ser.I, Goodman, Major
    See also Ser.I, Jain, H.K.
    See also Ser.I, North Carolina State College
    See also Ser.I, Timothy, David
    - Folder #1, 1959-1967 (Box 1)
    - Folder #2, 1968-1991 (Box 1)
  - Bukhari, A.I., 1979 (Box 1)
  - Burnham, Charles R., 1931-1932, 1962-1984, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Burr, Benjamin, 1978-1989 (Box 1)
    See also Ser.I, Cell
  - Carnegie Institution of Washington, 1967-1992; 75.0 Item(s) (Box 1)
    Singer, Maxine F.
    Carnegie Institution of Washington; Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory; Congratulations, greetings, thanks -- Nobel Prize; Congratulations, greetings, thanks -- Presidential medal; Fellowships, assistantships; Hershey, Alfred Day; History of biology, especially genetics -- Carnegie Institution of Washington; Research support; Solicitations for support or contribution; Watson, James D.; Women scientists
  - Cattanach, Bruce M., 1966-1967 (Box 2)
  - Cell, 1982 (Box 2)
    Burr, Benjamin
  - Chandler, Vicki L., 1989-1990 (Box 2)
  - Chen, Zhixiang, 1991 (Box 2)
    See also Ser.I, Klessig, Daniel F.
  - Chilton, Mary Dell, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Chomet, Paul S., 1985-1991 (Box 2)
  - Chou, Louise and Tom, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Chovnick, Arthur, 1975-1976 (Box 2)
  - Coe, Edward H., Jr., 1962-1988 (Box 2)
  - Cole, Jonathan R. (Box 2)
    See Ser.I, Zuckerman, Harriet
  - Columbia University, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Cone, Karen C., 1989 (Box 2)
  - Cooper, Kenneth W., 1971 (Box 2)
  - Cornell University, 1965-1990 (Box 2)
  - Crowell, Mignon, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Cutler, Hugh, 1966-1967 (Box 2)
    See also Ser.I, Timothy, David H.
  - Dellaporta, Stephen, 1972, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Doerschug, Earle, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Dooner, Hugo K., 1980-1990 (Box 2)
  - Döring, Peter, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Dusenbery, Ruth, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - Duvick, Donald N., 1985 (Box 2)
  - Dworkin, Martin, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Eagle, Harry, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Economic Botany, 1980 (Box 2)
    See also Ser.I, Goodman, Major M.
    See also Ser.IV, Goodman, Major M., J.S.C. Smith, Takeo A. Kato Y., Variation Within Teosinte
  - Emerson, R[ollins] A[dams], 1944; 1.0 Item(s) (Box 2)
    Cytogenetics; Genetics of plants
  - Emory University, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Fabergé, A.E., 1947 (Box 2)
  - Fedoroff, Nina, 1968-[1989] (Box 2)
  - Ficsor, Gyula, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Fincham, John R.S., 1973 (Box 2)
  - Flavell, R.B., 1982 (Box 2)
  - Fogel, Seymour, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Galinat, Walton C., 1972, 1975 (Box 2)
    Barghoorn, Elso S.
    Kornberg, Warren
    Lonnquist, John H.
    See also Ser.I, Kato Yamakake, Takeo Angel
  - Gall, Joseph Grafton, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Gavazzi, Giuseppe, 1964, 1966, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Gearhart, John David, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - Gembloux Agricultural College, 1985-1986 (Box 2)
  - Genetical Society, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Genetics, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    See also Ser.I, Sand, Seward A.
  - Genetics Society of America, Inc., 1981-1982 (Box 2)
  - Genetics Society of Canada, 1982-1983 (Box 2)
  - Gerstel, Daniel U., 1964 (Box 2)
  - Giles, Norman H., 1981-1982 (Box 2)
  - [Glass], [H.] Bentley, 1940 (Box 2)
  - Goodman, Major M., 1965-1982 (Box 2)
    See also Ser.I, Economic Botany
    See also Ser.IV, Goodman, Major, J.S.C. Smith, and Takeo A. Kato Y., Variation Within Teosinte
  - Grant, William C., Jr., n.d. (Box 2)
  - Green, Howard, [1979?] (Box 2)
  - Green, Melvin Martin, 1949, 1966-1973, 1984; 23.0 Item(s) (Box 2)
    Cytogenetics; Demerec, Milislav; Drosophila genetics; Fellowships, assistantships -- Guggenheim; Genetics; Lectures, public speaking; Molecular genetics; National Science Foundation; Publication -- Genetics; Publication -- Nobel Prize; Radiation genetics; Travel -- Invitations, arrangements; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.; Zea (maize) genetics
  - Grobman, Alexander, 1957-1959 (Box 2)
  - Harlan, Jack R., 1969 (Box 3)
  - Hartl, Daniel L., 1982 (Box 3)
  - Helfman, Arthur and Ruth, 1988 (Box 3)
  - Helfman, David Marc, 1991 (Box 3)
  - Henry, Susan, 1981 (Box 3)
  - Holt, H. John, 1983 (Box 3)
  - Louisa Gross Horwitz Prize (Box 3)
    See Ser.I, Columbia University
  - Hsu, Sun-Yuan, 1976 (Box 3)
  - Hu, Wilma, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Hutt, Fred B., 1970 (Box 3)
  - Hyams, Jeremy S., 1991 (Box 3)
  - Hyland, Howard L. (Box 3)
    See Ser.I, Brown, William L.
  - Iino, Tetsuo, 1983 (Box 3)
  - International Congress of Plant Molecular Biology, 1984 (Box 3)
    See also Ser.III, Mobile Genetic Elements. History and Prospectus
  - Ising, Gunnar, 1972 (Box 3)
  - Jain, H.K., 1972 (Box 3)
  - Jewell, David C., [1983?] (Box 3)
  - Jones, Jonathan, 1988 (Box 3)
  - Judd, Burke H., 1981 (Box 3)
  - Kato Yamakake, Takeo Angel, 1963-1984; 2 folders (Box 3)
    Galinat, Walton C.
    Wallace, Bruce
    See also Ser.I, Brown, William
    See also Ser.I, Galinat, Walton
    Beadle, George Wells; Biographical and personal data; Blumenschein, Almiro; Conferences and symposia; Congratulations, greetings, thanks; Cytogenetics; Evolution; Genetics of plants; Graduate study; Invitations; Laboratory techniques, equipment; Publication; Recommendations; Research support; Teaching; Travel -- Invitations, arrangements; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.; Wallace, Bruce; Zea (maize) genetics
    - Folder 1, 1963-1973 (Box 3)
    - Folder 2, 1974-1984 (Box 3)
  - Kermicle, Jerry L., 1962-1980 (Box 3)
    See also Ser.I, Klein, Anita
  - Kleckner, Nancy E., 1990 (Box 3)
  - Klein, Anita, 1982-1986 (Box 3)
    Kermicle, Jerry L.
  - Klessig, Daniel F., 1991 (Box 3)
    Chen, Zhixiang
  - Kornberg, Warren, 1972 (Box 3)
    See also Ser.I, Galiant, Walton C.
  - Kramer, Herbert H., 1950 (Box 3)
  - Krikorian, Abraham D., 1973, [1979?] (Box 3)
  - Lamb, Christopher J., 1991 (Box 3)
  - Lederberg, Joshua, 1948; 5.0 Item(s) (Box 3)
    Bacterial genetics; Bacteriophage and viral genetics; Genetics; Genetics of plants; Travel -- Invitations, arrangements; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.; Zea (maize) genetics
  - Lewis, Edward B., 1989 (Box 3)
  - Lindner, Deborah A., 1992 (Box 3)
  - Lonnquist, John H. (Box 3)
  - Lowe, Brenda Ann, 1987-1989 (Box 3)
  - Lyerla, Timothy A., 1983 (Box 3)
  - John D. and Catherine T. MacArthur Foundation, 1981-1989 (Box 3)
    See also Ser.II, same title
  - McClure, Marcella A., 1990 (Box 3)
  - McCormick, Sheila, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Mangelsdorf, Paul, 1958, 1972 (Box 3)
  - Margolin, Paul, 1984 (Box 3)
  - Marotta, Renzo (Box 3)
    See Ser.I, Salamini, Francesco
  - Martienssen, Robert, 1990 (Box 3)
    See also Ser.I, Barkan, Alice
  - Martínez, Maria Luísa, 1960, 1982 (Box 3)
    Some in Spanish
  - Masson, Patrick, 1990 (Box 3)
  - Charles Léopold Mayer Prize, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Medical Women's International Association, 1987 (Box 3)
  - Meins, Frederick, Jr., 1974 (Box 3)
  - Metz, C[harles] W., 1934, 1938 (Box 3)
  - Miami Winter Symposia, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Middlebury College, 1990 (Box 3)
  - Miller, George, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Mitchell, Christine, 1986 (Box 3)
  - Mooseker, Mark, 1991 (Box 4)
  - Monteiro, Warton, 1962-1964 (Box 4)
  - Moreno, Ulises (Box 4)
    See Ser.I, North Carolina State College
  - Thomas Hunt Morgan Centennial Symposium, 1967 (Box 4)
    See also Ser.III, The Expression of the Gene
  - Mottinger, John P., 1969, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Nanney, David Ledbetter, [1975] (Box 4)
  - Nasser, DeLill, 1989, 1991 (Box 4)
  - National Academy of Sciences, 1971, 1990-1991 (Box 4)
  - The National Foundation, 1975 (Box 4)
  - National Library of Medicine, 1986-1987 (Box 4)
  - National Research Council, 1957-1958 (Box 4)
  - Naturvetenskapliga Föreningen, 1984 (Box 4)
  - Nelson, Oliver E., Jr. (Box 4)
    Peterson, Peter A., 1967
    See also Ser.I, Genetics
    - Folder 1, 1961-1969 (Box 4)
    - Folder 2, 1970-1974 (Box 4)
    - Folder 3, 1974-1981 (Box 4)
    - Folder 4, 1982-1987 (Box 4)
    - Folder 5, 1988-1990 (Box 4)
  - Neuffer, M.G., 1965, 1979 (Box 4)
  - Nevers, Patricia, 1978 (Box 4)
    See also Ser.I, Saedler, Heinz
  - New York. Suffolk County, 1988 (Box 4)
  - New York University, 1983 (Box 4)
  - Nobel Prize, 1983, 1988 (Box 5)
  - North Carolina State College, 1961-1964 (Box 5)
    Moreno, Ulises
  - O'Brien, Stephen J., 1984-1986 (Box 5)
  - Ohta, Yasuo, 1963-1965 (Box 5)
  - O'Mara, Joe G., 1946-1947, n.d. (Box 5)
  - Osler, Robert D., 1959, 1970, 1984 (Box 5)
  - Paigen, Kenneth, 1966-1979 (Box 5)
  - Painter, Theophidus (Box 5)
    See Ser.I, Blumenschein, Almiro
  - Parratt, Patricia, 1986 (Box 5)
  - Peterson, Peter A., 1971-1984 (Box 5)
    Rhoades, Marcus M., 1972
    See also Ser.I, Nelson, Oliver E., Jr.
  - Phillips, Lyle L., 1964 (Box 5)
  - Phillips, Ronald L., 1970-1987, n.d. (Box 5)
  - Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 1974, 1989-1991 (Box 5)
  - Ptashne, Mark, 1982 (Box 5)
  - Ramsey, Ann, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Randolph, L.F., 1972 (Box 5)